Liberal Arts Records UA019
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Liberal Arts Records
1857 -- 1993
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Miller, Russell E.
School of Arts and Sciences
UA019
8.54 Linear Feet 15 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized in one series: Liberal Arts.
Custodial History
This collection, organized by subject, was created by Russell Miller while preparing his history of Tufts University, Light on the Hill.
All material accessioned prior to 1997 was originally arranged by subject, and no attempt was made to recreate original order. Material relating to administering the collection was removed to the documentation files of the collection in the archives. Most of the newsclippings, photographs, press releases, and correspondence have been separated from the subject files. These types of materials are present however, throughout the subject files as well.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the activities of a number of departments in the College of Liberal Arts and includes correspondence, course materials, meeting minutes, newspaper clippings, publications, photographs, reports, and scrapbooks.
Biographical / Historical
Russell Elliott Miller was a Professor of History, University Historian and Archivist of Tufts University, and author of "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts College from 1852 to 1952" and the second volume "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts University since 1952." He was born in Bloomington, Minnesota, on April 25, 1916, to one of the last pioneer families in the Minnesota prairie. His mother spoke Dakota Sioux, which she had learned as a child. He received a B.A. in Education in 1937 and an M.A. in political science in 1939, both from the University of Florida at Gainesville. From 1942 to 1946, he served in the Army Air Corps as an enlisted man, rising to the rank of technical sergeant. Initially with personnel and classification, he was finally assigned to the historical section (intelligence) at the headquarters of the troop carrier command. In 1948 he earned a Master of Arts in history from Princeton University and came to Tufts that same year.
In 1952 he received a PhD from Princeton, and in 1964 Tufts appointed him Professor of History and University Historian and archivist. He taught courses ranging from the history of western civilization to the history of the American frontier. In 1966, he published "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts College from 1852 to 1952." That year he received the Distinguished Service Award from the Tufts Alumni Association and became an honorary member of Phi Beta Kappa. In 1975 he became the Walter S. Dickson Professor of English and American History and chaired the Department of History from then until 1980. He was voted Emeritus Professor of English and American History in 1981 and received an honorary Doctor of Letters degree in 1983. In 1986, he completed the second volume of Tufts history, "Light on the Hill II, A History of Tufts University since 1952."
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Departments and Programs; Curriculum and Instruction -- Teaching Material
- Liberal Arts, 1857 -- 1993; UA019.001; 6.75 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series was created by Russell Miller while preparing his history of Tufts University, Light on the Hill. Includes material on a number of departments in the College of Liberal Arts, especially the drama and classics departments, including course material, playbills, and scrapbooks of Tufts productions. The following departments are represented in this series: Afro-American Studies, Astronomy, Biology, American studies, Chemistry, Classics, Computer Science, Economics, Education, English, Fine Arts, French, Geology, German and Russian, History, Mathematics, Music, Peace and Social Justice, Philosophy, Physical Education/Dance, Physics, Pre-Medical and Pre-Dental, Psychology, Religion, Romance Languages, Sociology, Women's Studies, and the Drama department.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - General, 1973 -- 1985; UA019.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Afro-American Studies, 1972 -- 1976; UA019.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Astronomy, 1925 -- 1951; UA019.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Biology, photos, 1937 -- 1961; UA019.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Biology, 1993; UA019.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Biology Dept., Harpswell Laboratory, 1909 -- 1985; UA019.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Biology, Woods Hole Marine Biological Lab, 1931 -- 1932; UA019.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - American Studies, 1987 -- 1991; UA019.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - American Studies mission statement: self study, 1988 -- 1989; UA019.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - American Studies, mission statement: appendices A-B, 1982; UA019.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - American Studies, mission statement: appendices C-D, 1982; UA019.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - American Studies, mission statement: appendices E-F, 1982; UA019.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - American Studies, mission statement: appendices G-H, 1982; UA019.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - American Studies, mission statement: appendices I-J, 1982; UA019.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - American Studies: mission statement: appendices K-O, 1982; UA019.001.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - American Studies, mission statement: appendix P, 1982; UA019.001.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - Center for Sudy of Decision Making, 1981; UA019.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Chemistry photos, 1950 -- 1975; UA019.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Chemistry, 1895 -- 1984; UA019.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Chemistry, correspondence, 1897 -- 1980; UA019.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Classics, 1901 -- 1984; UA019.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Classics, correspondence, 1857 -- 1963; UA019.001.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - Classics, enrollment statistics, 1965 -- 1967; UA019.001.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - Classics, faculty minutes, 1983 -- 1984; UA019.001.004.00004 (Box 4)
  - Classics, language placements, 1968 -- 1970; UA019.001.004.00005 (Box 4)
  - Classics, NDEA Fellowship, 1963 -- 1970; UA019.001.004.00006 (Box 4)
  - Classics, summer workshop, 1955; UA019.001.004.00007 (Box 4)
    Summer workshop also known as New England Classical Institute
  - Classics, summer workshop, 1956; UA019.001.004.00008 (Box 4)
  - Classics, summer workshop, 1957 -- 1960; UA019.001.004.00009 (Box 4)
  - Classics, summer workshop, 1961 -- 1964; UA019.001.004.00010 (Box 4)
  - Classics, summer workshop, 1965 -- 1967; UA019.001.005.00001 (Box 5)
  - Classics, summer workshop, 1968 -- 1969; UA019.001.005.00002 (Box 5)
  - Classics, summer workshop, 1970 -- 1974; UA019.001.005.00003 (Box 5)
  - Classics, summer workshop, 1975 -- 1985; UA019.001.005.00004 (Box 5)
    Also known as New England Classical Institute
  - College Within, 1970; UA019.001.005.00005 (Box 5)
  - Computer Science, 1979; UA019.001.005.00006 (Box 5)
  - Department of Economics, general, 1 of 2, 1940 -- 1965; UA019.001.044.00001 (Box Shared 75)
  - Department of Economics, general, 2 of 2, 1907 -- 1933; UA019.001.044.00002 (Box Shared 75)
  - Department of Economics, general, 2 of 2, 1933 -- 1974; UA019.001.044.00003 (Box Shared 75)
  - Department of Economics, Braker Fellowship, 1926 -- 1964; UA019.001.044.00004 (Box Shared 75)
  - Department of Economics, Braker Fund, 1908 -- 1963; UA019.001.044.00005 (Box Shared 75)
  - Department of Economics, Institute of Economic Research, 1947 -- 1958; UA019.001.044.00006 (Box Shared 75)
  - Department of Education, 1921 -- 1978; UA019.001.045.00001 (Box 45)
  - Department of Education, Faculty Minutes and Records, 1971 -- 1973; UA019.001.045.00002 (Box 45)
  - Department of Education, Faculty Minutes and Records, 1973 -- 1974; UA019.001.045.00003 (Box 45)
  - Department of Education, Faculty Minutes and Records, 1975 -- 1977; UA019.001.045.00004 (Box 45)
  - Department of Education, Tufts Summer Guidance Institute, 1972; UA019.001.045.00005 (Box 45)
  - Emporer's New Clothes, 1952; UA019.001.046.00001 (Box Shared 76)
  - The Hobbit., UA019.001.046.00002 (Box Shared 76)
  - The Man in the Moon, 1964; UA019.001.046.00003 (Box Shared 76)
  - The General's Daughter, UA019.001.046.00004 (Box Shared 76)
  - Department of English, 1900 -- 1975; UA019.001.047.00001 (Box 47)
  - Department of English, Oral Literature, 1975 -- 1978; UA019.001.047.00002 (Box 47)
  - Department of Fine Arts, 1930 -- 1982; UA019.001.048.00001 (Box 48)
  - Department of French, 1905 -- 1974; UA019.001.048.00002 (Box 48)
  - Department of Geography, UA019.001.048.00003 (Box 48)
  - Department of Geology, 1910 -- 1972; UA019.001.048.00004 (Box 48)
  - Department of German and Russian, 1906 -- 1991; UA019.001.048.00005 (Box 48)
  - Department of History, 1906 -- 1989; UA019.001.048.00006 (Box 48)
  - Department of Mathematics, 1905 -- 1975; UA019.001.049.00001 (Box 49)
  - Department of Mathematics, The Real Number System, Katz and Wilkinson, 1905 -- 1975; UA019.001.049.00002 (Box 49)
  - Department of Music, photos, 1940 -- 1960; UA019.001.049.00003 (Box 49)
  - Department of Music, copyright material, 1923 -- 1956; UA019.001.049.00004 (Box 49)
  - Department of Music, examinations, 1895 -- 1909; UA019.001.049.00005 (Box 49)
  - Department of Music, general, 1907 -- 1985; UA019.001.049.00006 (Box 49)
  - Peace and Social Justice Program, 1983; UA019.001.050.00001 (Box 50)
  - Department of Philosophy, 1907 -- 1989; UA019.001.050.00002 (Box 50)
  - Department of Physical Education/Dance, photos, 1930 -- 1970; UA019.001.050.00003 (Box 50)
  - Department of Physical Education/Dance, correspondence, 1959 -- 1976; UA019.001.050.00004 (Box 50)
  - Department of Physical Education/Athletics/Dance/Recreation, Annual Report, 1982 -- 1983; UA019.001.050.00005 (Box 50)
  - Department of Physical Education (Men), 1908 -- 1974; UA019.001.050.00006 (Box 50)
  - Department of Physical Education (Women), 1909 -- 1978; UA019.001.050.00007 (Box 50)
  - Department of Physics, photos, 1939 -- 1979; UA019.001.050.00008 (Box 50)
  - Department of Physics, general, 1908 -- 1983; UA019.001.050.00009 (Box 50)
  - Department of Physics, examinations, 1905 -- 1910; UA019.001.050.00010 (Box 50)
  - Plans of Study, 1974; UA019.001.050.00011 (Box 50)
  - Department of Political Science, general, 1940 -- 1966; UA019.001.050.00012 (Box 50)
  - Department of Political Science, Lowell Controversy, 1972; UA019.001.050.00013 (Box 50)
  - Pre-Medical and Pre-Dental Program, 1918 -- 1925; UA019.001.050.00014 (Box 50)
  - Department of Psychology, general, 1911 -- 1980; UA019.001.051.00001 (Box 51)
  - Department of Psychology, Institute for Psychological Research, 1950 -- 1969; UA019.001.051.00002 (Box 51)
  - Department of Religion, 1961 -- 1977; UA019.001.051.00003 (Box 51)
  - Department of Romance Languages, 1907 -- 1975; UA019.001.051.00004 (Box 51)
  - Department of Sociology, general, 1959 -- 1965; UA019.001.051.00005 (Box 51)
  - Department of Sociology, Contract Research, 1959 -- 1961; UA019.001.051.00006 (Box 51)
  - Department of Sociology, Research Grants, 1947 -- 1962; UA019.001.051.00007 (Box 51)
  - Department of Sociology, NEHA Project, 1960 -- 1962; UA019.001.051.00008 (Box 51)
  - Department of Sociology, Tufts-In-Italy, 1962 -- 1964; UA019.001.051.00009 (Box 51)
  - Liberal Arts: Women's Studies, 1983 -- 1992; UA019.001.051.00010 (Box 51)
  - Drama Department: Tufts Community Players -- production photographs, "The Rose Tattoo", 1954; UA019.001.052.00001 (Box Shared 77)
  - Drama Department: Photos, Junior Class Play, "The Other Way", 1909; UA019.001.053.00001 (Box Shared 78)